Guide to the African Postcard Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
African postcard collection
1900-2004
MS 1575
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
13.75
(28 boxes)
The collection consists of postcards depicting scenes from various countries on the African continent.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The collection must be used under the supervision of a Manuscripts and Archives Public Services staff member.
Associated Materials
African Collections for individual African countries. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by country.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of postcards depicting scenes from various countries on the African continent.
Postcards -- Africa; Africa -- Description and travel
- Original accession, 9 linear feet (18 boxes)
  - Africa
    - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Cards other than postcards (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - East Africa (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Swahili Coast (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - North Africa (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - West Africa (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 1, Folder 9-11)
  - Algeria
    - General (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - Book of postcards (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Algiers (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Biskrah (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Angola
    - General (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Alto-Dande (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Benguella (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Cards other than postcards (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Golungo-Alto (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Libollo (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Lobito (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Luanda (Loanda) (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Novo Redondo (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Benin (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Botswana
    - General (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Wildlife -birds (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Chobe and Okavango (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Wildlife -mammals (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Gaborone (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Kalahari Desert (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - People -village life (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Kanye and Mochudi (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Burkina Faso (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Burundi (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Cameroon (Box 2)
    - General (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Douala (Duala) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Yaounde (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Cape Verde Islands (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Book of postcards and fold-out postcard (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Central African Republic (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Chad (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Congo
    - Brazzaville (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Brazzaville -Mayumbe region (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Côte D'Ivoire: see Ivory Coast
  - Djibouti (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Egypt (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Equatorial Guinea (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Eritrea (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Ethiopia
    - General (Box 3, Folder 7-10)
    - Book of postcards (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Addis Ababa (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Assab (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Gabon (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - The Gambia
    - General (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Bathurst (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Ghana
    - General (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
    - Accra (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Fold-out postcard (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Ashanti (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Cape Coast (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Dodowah (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Kumasi (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Mining (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - Kwame Nkrumah (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Sekondi (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Tarkwah (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Guinea, French (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Guinea-Bissau (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Ivory Coast (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Kenya
    - General (Box 5, Folder 3-5)
      - postcards and accompanying material (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Mombasa (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Fold-out postcard (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Nairobi (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Lesotho
    - General (Box 6, Folder 2-3)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Mafeteng District (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Maseru (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Maseru District (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Mokhotlong District (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Philately (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Plants (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Qacha's Neck District (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Quthing District (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Liberia (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Libya (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Postcards and accompanying Material. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Madagascar (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Malawi (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Mali (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Set of postcards (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Mauritius (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Morocco (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Set of postcards (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Mozambique
    - General (Box 7, Folder 9)
      - Fold-out postcards (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Beira (Box 7, Folder 11)
      - Book of postcards (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Chinde (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Joao Belo (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Lourenco Marques (Maputo) (Box 7, Folder 15)
      - Additional material (Box 8, Folder 1)
      - Fold-out postcards (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Namibia (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
    - Book of postcards (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Niger (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Nigeria
    - General (Box 8, Folder 7-9)
      - Postcards and accompanying material, book of postcards (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Lagos (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Old Calabar (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Reunion (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Rwanda (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Saint Helena (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Sao Tome (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Senegal
    - General (Box 9, Folder 7-9)
    - Dakar (Box 9, Folder 10)
      - Book of postcards (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Seychelles Islands (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sierra Leone
    - General (Box 10, Folder 2-4)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 10, Folder 5)
      - Fold-out postcard (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Free Town (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
      - Fold-out postcards (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Somalia (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - South Africa
    - General (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Africans (Box 11, Folder 4-5)
      - Book of postcards (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Politica (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Cape Province
      - General (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Cape of Good Hope (Box 12, Folder 2)
        - Book of postcards (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - East London (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Cape Town (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Grahamstown (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Kimberley (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Port Elizabeth (Box 12, Folder 8)
        - Fold-our postcard (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Simon's Town (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Natal
      - General (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - Colenso (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Durban (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
      - Estcourt (Box 13, Folder 3)
      - Ladysmith (Box 13, Folder 4)
      - Pietermaritzburg (Box 13, Folder 5)
      - Zulu life (Box 13, Folder 6)
        - Fold-out postcard (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Orange Free State
      - General (Box 13, Folder 8)
      - Bloemfontein (Box 13, Folder 9)
      - Harrismith (Box 13, Folder 10)
      - Kroonstad (Box 13, Folder 11)
      - Parys (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Transvaal
      - General (Box 13, Folder 13)
      - Benoni (Box 13, Folder 14)
      - Bloemhof (Box 13, Folder 15)
      - Boksburg (Box 13, Folder 16)
      - Johannesburg
        - General (Box 13, Folder 17)
          - Additional material (Box 14, Folder 1)
          - Book of postcards (Box 14, Folder 2)
        - Mines on the Rand (Box 14, Folder 3)
        - Johannesburg region gold mines (Box 14, Folder 4)
      - Lydenberg (Box 14, Folder 5)
      - Messina (Box 14, Folder 6)
      - Potchefstroom (Box 14, Folder 7)
      - Pretoria (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Sudan
    - General (Box 14, Folder 9)
      - Additional material (Box 15, Folder 1-2)
      - Fold-out postcards (Box 15, Folder 3)
      - Postcards and accompanying materials (Box 15, Folder 4)
      - Book of postcards (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Sudan-Khartoum, 'Sudan Postcard Album', Circa 1920-1935 (Box 15, Folder 6-7)
  - Swaziland (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Tanzania
    - General (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
      - Postcards and accompanying material, Circa 1965 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Dar es Salam (Box 16, Folder 4)
      - Book of postcards (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Tanga (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Zanzibar (Box 16, Folder 7-8)
      - Book of postcards, fold-out postcard (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - Togo (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Fold-out postcard, Circa 1910 (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - Tunisia
    - General (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Tunis (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Qayrawan (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Uganda (Box 17, Folder 4-5)
    - Postcards and acompanyinig material, fold-out postcard (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Western Sahara (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Zaire (Congo Democratic Republic)
    - General (Box 17, Folder 8-10)
      - Book of postcards (Box 17, Folder 11)
    - Banana (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Boma (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Coquilhatville (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Elizabethville (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Katanga (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - Book of postcards (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - Kinshasa (Leopoldville) (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Kivu (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Likasi (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - Matadi (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Stanleyville, Stanleyfalls (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Zambia (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Zimbabwe
    - General (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - Bulawayo (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Ruins (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Salisbury / Harare (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Umtali (Box 18, Folder 17)
      - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 18, Folder 18)
- Additional material, Accession 1998-M-041; 2.5 linear feet (5 boxes)
  - Africa, general (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - East Africa
      - General (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - East Africa [photographed by G. Cooper; privately printed] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - West Africa
      - General (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - West Africa [photographed by G. Cooper; privately printed] (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Francophone West Africa (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Angola (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Benin (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Botswana (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Burkina Faso (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Cameroon (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cape Verde (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Central African Republic (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Chad (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Comores (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Congo (Democratic Republic) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Congo (Brazzaville) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Postcards and accompanying materials (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Djibouti (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Eritrea (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Book of fold-out postcards (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Ethiopia
    - General (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Afewerk Tekle paintings postcards and accompanying material (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gabon (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Gambia (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Ghana (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Postcards and accompanying materials (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Guinea (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ivory Coast (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Kenya
    - General (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Postcards and accompanying materials (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Mombasa (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Nairobi (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lesotho
    - General (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Maseru (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Liberia (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Libya (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Madagascar (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Madeira (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Malawi (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Mali (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Book of postcards (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Mozambique
    - General (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Set of postcards (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Beira (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Lourenco Marques (Maputo) (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Namibia
    - General (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - German South West Africa (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Niger (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Nigeria
    - General (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Lagos (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reunion (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Rwanda (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Book of postcards (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Senegal
    - General (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Dakar (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Set of postcards (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Books of postcards (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Sierra Leone
    - General (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Freetown (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Somalia (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - South Africa
    - General (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
      - Book of postcards (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - Set of postcards (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Africans (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - British Army - Harrismith (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Politica (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Cape of Good Hope [formerly Cape Province]
      - Cradock (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Kimberley (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Small towns (Box 4, Folder 16)
        - Fold-out postcard (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Cape Town (Box 5, Folder 1)
      - Fold-out postcards (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Natal
      - General (Box 5, Folder 3)
      - Pietermaritzburg (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Orange Free State
      - General (Box 5, Folder 5)
      - Jagersfontein (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Transvaal
      - General (Box 5, Folder 7)
      - Bloemhof (Box 5, Folder 8)
      - Burghersdorp (Box 5, Folder 9)
      - Johannesburg (Box 5, Folder 10)
      - Potchefstroom (Box 5, Folder 11)
      - Pretoria (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Sudan (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Swaziland (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Tanzania
    - General (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Dar es Salam (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Zanzibar (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Uganda (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Zaire (Congo Democratic Republic) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Zambia (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Zimbabwe
    - General (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Bulawayo (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Salisbury / Harare (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Victoria Falls (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Additional material, Accession 2009-M-059; 1.25 linear feet (3 boxes)
  - Angola (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Benin (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Burundi (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Cameroon (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Central African Republic (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Chad (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Congo: Brazaville (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Congo (Democratic Republic) (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
    - De Belgique au Congo (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Elizabethville (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Exposition de Gand en Afrique Belge, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Kigoma (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Tervuren (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Huileries du Congo Belge (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Souvenirs du Congo (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Souvenir du Voyage du Prince Léopold (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Kinshasa and Leopoldville (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Cote d'Ivoire (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Djibouti (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Eritrea (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ethiopia (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Guerra Italo-Etiopica (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Gabon (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gambia (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - German East Africa (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Kenya (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Lesotho (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Liberia (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Mali (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Postcards and accompanying material (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mozambique (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Perroux, François (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Mauritania (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Namibia (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Niger (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Musiciens traditionnels (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rwanda (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Sao Tome (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Santa Casa de Misericórdia (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Senegal (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sierra Leone (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Somalia (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Graziani's visit to Mogadishu (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - South Africa (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sudan (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Buchanan expedition of crossing the Great Sahara (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Tanzania (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Togo (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Additional material, Accession 2014-M-016; 1; (2 boxes)
  - Angola (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Belgian Congo (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Benin (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Burkina Faso (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Burundi (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Cameroon (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cape Verde (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Central African Republic (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chad (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Cote d'Ivoire (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Ethiopia (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Gabon (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gambia (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ghana (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Guinea (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Kenya (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lesotho (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Madagascar (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Mali (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Mauritania (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Namibia (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Niger (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Nigeria (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Reunion (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Rwanda (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Senegal (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Sierra Leone (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Somalia (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - South Africa (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Sudan (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Swaziland (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Tanzania (Zanzibar) (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Togo (Dahomey) (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Tunisia (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Uganda (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Zaire (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Zambia (Northern Rhodesia) (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Zimbabwe (Rhodesia) (Box 2, Folder 23)